We've known for quite some time that
fasting and calorie restriction as a
whole extends lifespan. While most of
these studies are done in non-humans, we
have data at least indicating that this
is also true for humans, even if we
can't deprive grandma of food for 10
years to see if she'll outlive the other
grandmas on the block. And don't get any
ideas.
But recently, it's been shown that a
single nutrient actually mimics fasting
and long-term calorie restriction
without even needing to restrict
calories. In fact, quite the opposite as
shown here. Don't worry, there isn't
much to this. This is a measure of food
consumption. If the bars are higher,
that means more food was consumed. I'm
only interested in showing you the far
left bar in red and the far right bar in
orange. The far left is the calorie
restricted condition and the calorie
restriction was accomplished through
fasting. The far right bar is the group
that consumed the nutrient. Clearly, the
nutrient group consumed a lot more food.
And I'll go ahead and tell you that they
weighed more, too. Not more than normal,
but more than the calorie restricted
group, the fasting group. And since
protein is also an area of heavy study
in relation to longevity, I'll tell you
now that they consumed more protein,
too. The nutrient I'm talking about is
dietary fiber. Now, when researchers
compared the liver gene signatures,
meaning these genes related to longevity
are upregulated or read more or
downregulated, read less, among animals
fasted and calorie restricted versus
those on a normal diet versus those fed
dietary fiber, they discovered an
intriguing pattern. Now, I realize this
looks like a lot, but it's a simple to
read. All you have to do is look at the
similarities in color. The more blue,
the less those genes are read or
expressed. And if it's red, those genes
are expressed or read more. I'll even
create boxes for you so that you can uh
focus on each grouping of genes. The CR
is the calorie restricted, so the
fasting condition. The RD is the regular
diet, the control condition. And the
only other one that we're interested in
is the CF30M
there. If you compare the colors, so the
gene signatures, the fasting condition
and that fiber condition are far more
similar with blue up top and red down
below, while the regular diet, the
control, is the opposite. So, we're
seeing the mimicry of the fiber diet
mimicking the anti-aging
longevity-proven calorie restriction and
fasting. The takeaway is that a
high-fiber diet mimics the longevity
signatures of fasting and calorie
restriction, although no calorie
restriction or fasting is occurring.
Pretty incredible. Now, the discoveries
here are fascinating, but there are a
few things to consider here. For one,
there aren't any actual longevity
measurements made. So, other studies
have actually looked at longevity, but
that's missing from this study. I go
over uh some functional measurements on
muscle as well as insulin resistance and
even hair graying in my full analysis,
which is in the extended video and
article exclusive for the Physiologic
Insiders if you're interested. The link
to join is in the description. You also
also get all these perks right here if
you uh want to discuss it with me in
live sessions or with the community
there. Even with these measurements,
though, there's no actual survival data
measured from longevity outright. Other
questions that I have beyond the fact
that
these measurements are in animals is if
these similarities in gene signatures
between the fiber and fasting, so the
calorie restricted group, continue over
time. Because these measures are made
over a short period of time. Now, a
month, which for mice is a long time,
but I'd want to see more.
But while we may not have a head-to-head
comparison in humans like we're looking
at here, one, this kind of study over a
few months could be done in humans. But
beyond that, we have overwhelming
evidence that fiber does protect against
mortality. So, is it much of a gamble to
prioritize fiber consumption?
Probably not, unless you have
gastrointestinal issues or some other
relatively niche reason not to. Now,
while I would like to see more, there
are a few things that we can take away
from this. One, clearly a fiber-rich
diet has parallels to a
calorie-restricted diet and fasting
without even needing to cut calories or
fast, which is pretty remarkable when
you think about it. These data haven't
been directly compared in humans yet and
may not be a complete replacement, but
it opens the possibility. And two,
high-fiber diets consistently show
benefits in humans in relation to
reducing mortality risk. So, this may be
yet another way that we're seeing that
manifest. So, if your fiber consumption
is low and you don't have any other
reason that you can't consume fiber,
this is another reminder to pay
attention to fiber consumption. In fact,
if you need even more guidance and more
encouragement, I cover a lot of the
protective effects of fiber right here.
Thanks for tuning in. I'll speak with
you soon.